YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 6. Program: Series VI. Publications
Sophia Smith Collection
YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 06. Program: Series VI. Publications
1870-2002
Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A.
324_rg6_s6
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
This series documents the YWCA's extensive publications program including its Womans Press. Materials include Publications Department minutes, correspondence, reports, catalogs, and advertising. The series also includes some of the voluminous output of publications. Forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 6. Program.
Historical Note
Early in its history, the YWCA of the U.S.A. established a Publication Department to publish its monthly magazine, then known as the Association Monthly; to produce study materials, programs, and other publications for the National Convention and for conferences; and to facilitate and oversee publication, promotion, and distribution of "technical" publications written by and for the Association's departments and divisions.
In the spring of 1916 the Publication Department and Committee started discussing a plan for enlarging the publishing venture. The idea was to finance the Association's "technical" publications through sales of more general interest material which could "Christianize the Woman's Movement." In the spring of 1917 they consulted with National Association staff, librarians, teachers, and social workers "to discover what sort of books they looked for…but did not find." These groups cited a real need for "books on vocations, written for girls; books on personal efficiency; biographies; collections of poetry; stories which will help the modern-day woman to adjust herself to the world in which she lives; and reprints in attractive form of books or parts of books which every girl ought to read." (Association Monthly, June 1917) The Department settled on a new name, The Womans Press, to reflect the more general character of the venture. (For its first 28 years, 1917-45, the name was usually printed without an apostrophe.) The first two titles under the new imprint, Mobilizing Woman-Power by Harriot Stanton Blatch and The Young Woman Citizen by Mary Austin went on sale in 1918.
In addition to their work on production and distribution of technical publications (which were generally written by staff most closely involved with the subject), the Publications Department selected authors and editors for the new general interest books, oversaw their design, publication, publicity, and distribution; produced the monthly magazine (re-christened The Womans Press) and Convention publications; and administered the Woman's Bookshop in the National headquarters.
The hard-cover general interest titles included religious books, such as collections of prayers and meditations, books on How to Use the Bible, and Christianity's relation to communism, peace, work, citizenship, and social morality. The Association also published poetry collections, women's memoirs and biographies, and books on women in history. Many titles reflected the staff's areas of expertise, presenting topics such as group work, adolescent girls' development, race relations, international understanding, health, jobs, citizenship, leadership, and sex education. Recreation and creative expression were promoted through volumes about nature study, flower arranging, parties, festivals, and Decorating the Small Apartment.
The impressive catalog of "technical" publications on a myriad of topics made up one of the most important contributions of the National Association to Community and Student Associations. The publications were clear, comprehensive, attractive, and eminently useful.
In the face of the financial challenges of the Depression, the Publications Department adjusted such things as the quality of the paper and formality of presentation, and managed to continue to put out a substantial catalog of titles.
Paper and other shortages curtailed publication during World War II. After the war, the National Association attempted a revival on advice of a "business analyst." A three-year plan concentrated in three major subject areas appropriate to YWCA: social group work, religion, and self-help books for women. The records are vague about why the Association ultimately abandoned this plan, but it eventually decided to sell its rights in the "general interest" hardcover books to Whiteside, Inc., in 1952. As part of the agreement, the National Association promised to limit its future publications to items for use within the Association and not to enter the publishing business in any form.
The National Association continued to put out technical and publicity materials, but on a much smaller scale. In 1961, the efforts became the responsibility of the Communications Bureau.
Administrative History
1909-12 Publication Department
1912-22 Publication Department
1923-24 Editorial Department in Editorial and Publicity Division
1923-32 program staff decentralized in Field Division and Education and Research Division
1925-31 Education and Research Division
1932-39 Publications in Laboratory Division
1940-49 Publication Department
1950-51 Publications Services in Membership Resources and Woman's Press in General Administration
1951-53 Publications Services in Membership Resources
1954-60 Publications Services in General Administration
1961- part of Communications Bureau in Executive Office
Scope and Contents
Forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records--Record Group 6. Program.
NOTE: For the most part, the Microfilmed Records and the Original Format Records do not duplicate each other and both should be consulted. This description covers materials in both formats. See the Contents List for a folder-level inventory of the Original Format Records. See the Microfilmed Records Reel Lists for a detailed inventory of the microfilm.
The records in this series include Publications Department minutes, correspondence, reports, catalogs, and advertising. They document the work of those making decisions about the general interest publications, coordinating and scheduling all of the publications, and overseeing production. There are significant gaps in the minutes and only a few years of records of the production side of the operation, yet what survives provides significant insight into this aspect of the National program.
The series also includes some of the voluminous output of publications. Those that are filed with this series are the main Association-wide serials, the general interest books, and gift and keepsake items, such as engagement calendars. Other publications are filed with related records in other Series and Record Groups throughout the Records. For example, play scripts are in Pageantry and Drama, and the serial Foreign Born is in Immigration and Foreign Communities.
The National Board Library at YWCA headquarters in New York kept copies of many of the publications. That collection was transferred to the Sophia Smith Collection with the rest of the records. It is difficult to say for certain whether the collection, which consists of approximately 1700 books, pamphlets, scripts, serials, and other types of publications is complete. There are some projects mentioned in the minutes, for instance, that may not ultimately have been published, or may have been published under a different title.
Many publications were microfilmed. These were mainly the "technical" items and only rarely the hard-cover books.
For general information about the National Association and Community Associations, the Association Monthly/Womans Press/YWCA Magazine is an unparalleled source. In addition to the articles and columns, details of Association history can be traced through such things as staff and committee rosters, "secretarial changes," conference schedules, news from Community Associations, and conference and convention reports.
When the YWCA Records were transferred to the Sophia Smith Collection, they included multiple copies of many publications. The processing staff took advantage of this bounty, to file duplicates in multiple places where applicable-for instance, booklets about training Girl Reserve workers could be filed both in Training and Teenage Program.
Microfilmed Records, 1907-71
[see Microfilmed Records Reel List]
In addition to Committee records listed below, many YWCA publications were microfilmed with other records related to their subject or department. They are usually located in the "Miscellaneous" section at the end of each Subject in the Subject Files. The main serials were not microfilmed.
Records relating to YWCA publishing efforts can be found on the microfilm under:
Minutes and Reports
Communications Committee
Publications Services Committee
Publication Department and Woman's Press Committee
Publications, Committee on Correlation of
Woman's Press Committee
Subject Files
Copyrights
Publications Services
Reprint Privilege
Woman's Press [reel lost]
Original Format Records, 1907-98, n.d., circa 20 linear feet
[see Original Format Records folder list]
The Departmental office files in the Original Format Records include hard copy of the minutes and reports that are also on the microfilm; Womans Press and other publications catalogs; advertising; a few "Schedules" forms for proposed publications and reprints from the 1930s; and card file title indexes to YWCA publications.
Publications filed with this series include the main Association-wide serials, the hard-cover "general interest" books, and gift and keepsake publications such as engagement calendars.
The Association's main serial, The Association Monthly/Womans Press/YWCA Magazine is an excellent source for tracing the history of the YWCA publishing through its articles, but also through the advertising and publications announcements.
Related Materials
"Technical" publications can be found throughout the records, usually in the Publications section within a series or subseries.
In other Series in this Record Group
The Publications Department was sometimes under the administrative supervision of other departments or divisions, usually the "program"-related departments. Additional information can be found in the department/division minutes in SERIES I. DEPARTMENT, STAFF, AND COMMITTEES.
In other Record Groups
In later years, the Publications were the responsibility of the Publicity staff, Additional information can be found in SERIES VI. PUBLICITY of RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE.
Records about the sale of the Woman's Press general interest titles in 1952 are in SERIES III. FINANCE AND DEVELOPMENT under Comptroller's Office in RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINSTRATIVE OFFICE.
Legal files with information about publications copyrights are in SERIES I. GENERAL ADMINISTRATION of RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINSTRATIVE OFFICE.
A major part of the mission of the Publications Department was responsibility for Convention and Conference publications filed in RECORD GROUP 4. NATIONAL CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES.
The records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies.
Additional Formats
A copy of the microfilmed records of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records is available to borrow from the William Allan Neilson Library at Smith College via Interlibrary Loan.
To request the microfilm from our library you will need to submit the following information to your library's Interlibrary Loan department:
Author: Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. National Board
Title: Records, 1876-1970 [microform]
WorldCat Accession Number: OCLC 57415795
Notes: "Call # 689" and reel number(s) you want to borrow
Full descriptions and reel lists of the microfilm are available online.
The YWCA of the U.S.A. donated a portion of its records to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1964 and the remainder in 2002 and 2003.
McCulloch, Rhoda Elizabeth, 1884-
Record Groups
The YWCA of the USA Records are arranged as follows:
YWCA of the U.S.A. Records (main record)
RECORD GROUP 1. GENERAL AND HISTORY
RECORD GROUP 2. PREDECESSOR ORGANIZATIONS AND NATIONAL BOARD
RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE
RECORD GROUP 4. NATIONAL CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES
RECORD GROUP 5. INTERNATIONAL WORK
RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM
SERIES I. DEPARTMENT, STAFF, AND COMMITTEES
SERIES II. TRAINING AND PERSONNEL
SERIES III. PUBLIC ADVOCACY
SERIES IV. CONSTITUENT GROUPS
SERIES V. PROGRAM SUBJECTS
SERIES VI. PUBLICATIONS
SERIES VII. WAR WORK AND DEFENSE SERVICES
RECORD GROUP 7. STUDENT WORK
RECORD GROUP 8. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS
RECORD GROUP 9. PHOTOGRAPHS
RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS
Artifacts
The Microfilmed Records
The Oversized Materials
This Record group forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records
- SERIES VI. PUBLICATIONS
  This is the Contents List for the Original Format Records only. The reel lists for the Microfilmed Records are in a separate file. See Scope and Content note for more description.
  - General, 1918-89, n.d. (Box 660A, Folder 1)
  - Publications Committee/Publications Services Committee
    - Minutes, 1907-24 (Box 660A, Folder 2-8)
    - Agendas, 1932-37 (Box 660A, Folder 9-10)
    - Minutes
      - 1932-33, 1940-49 (Box 660A, Folder 11-16)
      - 1950-61 (Box 660B, Folder 1-5)
  - Correlation of Publications Committee: minutes, 1920-24 (Box 660B, Folder 6-10)
  - Woman's Press Committee: minutes, 1950-51 (Box 660B, Folder 11)
  - Reports
    - Publications Department
      - 1907-15 (Box 660B, Folder 12-18)
      - 1916-21, 1924, n.d. (Box 661, Folder 1-6)
    - Biennial, 5-year, 1914-20 (Box 661, Folder 7)
  - "Schedules" (Form for Proposed Publications and Reruns), 1932-33, 1935-37 (Box 661, Folder 8-11)
  - Publications catalogs
    - 1914-15, 1926, 1937, 1940-1945/46 (Box 661, Folder 12-15)
    - 1946/47-70 (Box 662, Folder 1-4)
  - Publicity materials for Womans Press publications
    - Miscellaneous lists, 1930-47, n.d. (Box 662, Folder 5)
    - Christmas, 1947, n.d. (Box 662, Folder 6)
    - Inserts for complementary/promotion copies, circa 1926-80, n.d. (Box 662, Folder 7)
    - YWCA serials, circa 1926-72, n.d. (Box 662, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous publications, 1935-88, n.d. (Box 662, Folder 9)
    - Serials Indexes
      - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 662, Folder 10)
      - The Bookshelf, 1930-72 (Box 662, Folder 11)
      - International Messenger, 1894-1902 (selective) (Box 662, Folder 12)
      - Evangel, 1888-1906 (selective) (Box 662, Folder 13)
      - War Work Bulletin, 1917-19 (Box 662, Folder 14)
      - Womans Press/YWCA Magazine, 1930-77 (Box 662, Folder 15)
      - World YWCA Monthly, 1963-70 (Box 662, Folder 16)
      - YWCA Interchange, 1974-86 (Box 662, Folder 17)
  - Card files
    - Title Index to YWCA Publications, 1901-70
      - A-Ph 1901-70 (Box 663)
      - Pi-Z, and those beginning "YWCA…" 1901-70 (Box 664)
    - Publication Series and Subject Index; Bureau of Communications Publications record cards (includes cost and number ordered); and Woman's Press Titles with copyright transferred to Whiteside 1901-70 (Box 665)
  - Miscellaneous publications
    - Christmas stories, 1921, 1942-45 (Box 666, Folder 1)
    - Edit Your Own Copy, Womans Press style manual, 1940, 1942 (Box 666, Folder 2)
    - Pocketbook Bibliographies, 1934 (Box 666, Folder 3)
  - Calendars
    - YWCA Calendar
      - 1909, 1911-15 (Box 666, Folder 4-9)
      - 1916-18 (Box 667, Folder 1-3)
    - Modern Readers Calendar
      - 1920-22, 1925 (Box 667, Folder 4-7)
      - 1926-28 (Box 668, Folder 1-3)
    - Calendar, 1937-39 (Box 668, Folder 4-6)
    - Engagement Calendar
      - 1947-48 (Box 668, Folder 7-8)
      - 1949 (Box 669, Folder 1)
    - Pop-up calendars, 1984-92 (Box 669, Folder 2)
  - Books
    - Lyman Abbott, The Crucifers, 1923 (Box 669, Folder 3)
    - Barbara Abel, Follow the Leadership and Other Skits, 1938 (Box 669, Folder 4)
    - Charlotte Adams, Women of Ancient Israel, 1916 (Box 669, Folder 5)
    - Katharine L. Aller Along the Bethlehem Way, 1941 (Box 669, Folder 6)
    - George H. Atkinson Frances Bridges Atkinson, 1908 (Box 669, Folder 7)
    - Mary Austin
      - The Young Woman Citizen, 1918 (Box 669, Folder 8)
      - Young Woman in the New Social Order, study outline for use with the Young Woman Citizen, 1919 (Box 669, Folder 9)
    - Lucy T. Bartlett, compiler, Services for Special Needs, 1941 (Box 669, Folder 10)
    - Katherine Lee Bates
      - Little Robin Stay-Behind, 1923 (Box 669, Folder 11)
      - The Pilgrim Ship, 1926 (Box 669, Folder 12)
    - John C. Bennett Christianity and Communism, 1948 (Box 669, Folder 13)
    - Peter Bertocci The Human Venture in Sex, Love, and Marriage, 1949 (Box 669, Folder 14)
    - Harriot Stanton Blatch Mobilizing Woman-Power, 1918, and A Woman's Point of View, 1920 (Box 669, Folder 15)
    - Ella Bowles Practical Parties, 1926 (Box 669, Folder 16)
    - Stella Burgess Toward the Summit, 1948 (Box 669, Folder 17)
    - Margaret Burton
      - Comrades in Service, 1915 (Box 669, Folder 18)
      - Mabel Cratty: Leader in the Art of Leadership, 1929 (Box 669, Folder 19)
      - Remember April, 1941 (Box 669, Folder 20)
      - The Star-Promise, 1925 (Box 669, Folder 21)
    - Emma Byers Out of Doors with Birds, 1937 (Box 669, Folder 22)
    - Richard Cabot The Christian Approach to Social Morality, 1913 (Box 669, Folder 23)
    - Vivian Campbell A Christmas Anthology of Poetry and Painting, 1947 (Box 670, Folder 1)
    - Adelaide Teague Case The Servant of the Lord: a Devotional Commentary, 1940 (Box 670, Folder 2)
    - Margaret Clark and Briseis Teall The Executive Director on the Job, 1947 (Box 670, Folder 3)
    - Elspeth Clarke The Joy of Service: Memoirs of Elizabeth Dodge Huntington Clarke, 1979 (Box 670, Folder 4-5)
    - Alice Collins Methods in Group Work, 1938 (Box 670, Folder 6)
    - Bertha Cond?é The Human Element in the making of a Christian, 1917 (Box 670, Folder 7)
    - Grace Coyle
      - Group Experience and Democratic Values, 1947 (Box 670, Folder 8)
      - Jobs and Marriage?, 1928 (Box 670, Folder 9)
    - Brooks Spivey Creedy Women Behind the Lines, 1949 (Box 670, Folder 10)
    - Martha Foote Crow Christ in the Poetry of Today, 1917, 1918, 1923 (Box 670, Folder 11-12)
    - Marion Cuthbert
      - April Grasses, 1936 (Box 670, Folder 13)
      - Juliette Derricotte, 1936, and Songs of Creation, 1949 (Box 670, Folder 14)
    - Ethel Cutler One People Among Many: The Ancient Hebrews and Their Neighbors, 1942, and One Prophet - and Another, 1942 (Box 670, Folder 15)
    - Anne Darlington Yelenka the Wise, 1926 (Box 670, Folder 16)
    - Enid Day Adventures of a Nurse's Aid, 1951 (Box 670, Folder 17)
    - Frances Densmore The American Indians and Their Music, 1926 (Box 670, Folder 18)
    - Sarah Truslow Dickinson, compiler, Fellowship Prayers, 1928 (Box 670, Folder 19)
    - Fyodor Dostoyevsky The Grand Inquisitor, 1948 (Box 670, Folder 20)
    - Marion Dudley Explorers, 1926 (Box 670, Folder 21)
    - Carlisle Ellis Red Shoes, 1930 (Box 671, Folder 1)
    - Mary G. Ellsworth Birthday Parties for Boys and Girls, 1951 (Box 671, Folder 2)
    - Victoria Emerson Into the World, 1950 (Box 671, Folder 3)
    - L. Wendell Fifield How to Use the Bible, 1920 (Box 671, Folder 4)
    - Jack Finegan Youth Asks About Religion, 1949 (Box 671, Folder 5)
    - Welthy Fisher A String of Chinese Pearls, 1924 (Box 671, Folder 6)
    - R. Louise Fitch Madame France, 1919 (Box 671, Folder 7)
    - Harry Emerson Fosdick The Challenge of the Present Crisis, 1917 (Box 671, Folder 8)
    - Stephen Hole Frichtman, editor, Prayers of the Free Spirit, 1945 (Box 671, Folder 9)
    - Edith Gates Health Through Leisure-Time Recreation, 1931 (Box 671, Folder 10)
    - Josephine H. Gerth Highways to Jobs for Women, 1948 (Box 671, Folder 11)
    - Hazel Gewinner Lalah of the Mountain, 1924 (Box 671, Folder 12)
    - Emily Gibson English-Class Plays for New Americans, 1927 (Box 671, Folder 13)
    - Charles Gilkey New Frontiers of Faith, 1927 (Box 671, Folder 14)
    - Girl Reserve staff The Girl Reserve Movement, 1924 (Box 671, Folder 15)
    - Abbie Graham
      - Ceremonials of Common Days, 1923, 1925, 1942 (Box 671, Folder 16-17)
      - The Girls' Camp, 1933, and Working at Play in Summer Camp, 1941 (Box 671, Folder 18)
      - Grace H. Dodge: Merchant of Dreams, 1926 (Box 671, Folder 19)
      - High Occasions, 1930 (Box 672, Folder 1)
      - Ladies in Revolt, 1934, On Being Immortal, 1942, and Outposts of the Imagination: A Travel Guide to Cities by Way of Historical Fiction, 1930 (Box 672, Folder 2)
      - Time Off and On, 1939 (Box 672, Folder 3)
      - Vain Pomp and Glory, 1927 (Box 672, Folder 4)
    - Ivan Grimshaw How to Prepare a Speech, 1952 (Box 672, Folder 5)
    - Eva Hansl Trends in Part Time Employment for College Trained Women, 1949 (Box 672, Folder 6)
    - Louise Hasbrouck The Hall With Doors, 1920 (Box 672, Folder 7)
    - Charles Hendry The Role of Groups in World Reconstruction, 1952 (Box 672, Folder 8)
    - Margaret Hiller Leadership in the Making, 1936, 1939 (Box 672, Folder 9)
    - Margaret Hodgen Factory Work for Girls, 1919, 1920 (Box 672, Folder 10)
    - Imogene Ireland The Song Book of the YWCA, 1926 (Box 672, Folder 11)
    - Annie B. Kerr
      - Candles in the Heart,1939, The Christmas Guest, 1944, and Clear Shining After Rain, 1941 (Box 672, Folder 12)
      - So Gracious the Time, 1938, and So Many Pathways, 1940 (Box 672, Folder 13)
      - Wednesdays, 1929 (Box 672, Folder 14)
    - Laura Kerr Lady in the Pulpit, 1951 (Box 672, Folder 15)
    - Winifred Kirkland The Christmas Shrine, 1920, and The Man Who Gave Us Christmas, 1940 (Box 672, Folder 16)
    - Bertha Palmer Lane Lad and Other Story Plays, 1926 (Box 672, Folder 17)
    - Tolman Lee Funds and Friends, 1925 (Box 672, Folder 18)
    - Anne W. Lindsay Group Work Recording, 1952 (Box 672, Folder 19)
    - D. Willard Lyon The Christian Equivalent of War, 1915 (Box 672, Folder 20)
    - Kathleen Macarthur The Bible and Human Rights, 1948 (Box 673, Folder 1)
    - Anne Marion MacLean Cheero!, 1918 (Box 673, Folder 2)
    - Jeannette Marks Courage, 1919 (Box 673, Folder 3)
    - Rhoda McCulloch Little Talks on Large Topics, 1930 (Box 673, Folder 4)
    - Alexander Miller Christian Faith and My Job, 1946 (Box 673, Folder 5)
    - Clelia Duel Mosher Woman's Physical Freedom, 1923 (Box 673, Folder 6)
    - Janet Fowler Nelson Marriages Are Not Made in Heaven, 1939 (Box 673, Folder 7)
    - Elizabeth Ogg Decorating the Small Apartment, 1949 (Box 673, Folder 8)
    - A. Estelle Paddock Overtaking the Centuries, 1916 (Box 673, Folder 9)
    - Margaret Parsons Red Letter Day Plays, 1921, and One Night Stand and Other Plays, 1942 (Box 673, Folder 10)
    - Esther Peck National Costumes of the Slavic Peoples, 1920 (Box 673, Folder 11)
    - Ruth Perkins Magic Casements, 1927, and Program Making and Record Keeping, 1931 (Box 673, Folder 12)
    - Alexander Purdy
      - Jesus' Way with People, 1926, and Pathways to God, 1922 (Box 673, Folder 13)
      - The Way of Christ, 1918, 1929 (Box 673, Folder 14)
    - Margaret S. Quayle As Told to Business Girls, 1932 (Box 673, Folder 15)
    - Anna V. Rice History of the World's YWCA, 1947 (Box 673, Folder 16)
    - Jean Rich (pseudo. for Helen Frances Thompson) Dos and Don'ts for Business Women, 1922 (Box 673, Folder 17)
    - Richard Roberts
      - The Ascending Life, 1924 (Box 673, Folder 18)
      - Florence Simms: A Biography, 1926; The Untried Door: An Attempt to Discover the Mind of Jesus for Today, 1921 (Box 674, Folder 1)
    - Duane Robinson Chance to Belong, 1949 (Box 674, Folder 2)
    - Marion Robinson Eight Women of the YWCA, 1966 (Box 674, Folder 3)
    - Matilda Rogers Flower Arrangement: A Hobby for All, 1949 (Box 674, Folder 4)